<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="keepass2-xml-rfc">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private="yes"?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="KeePass2 XML">KeePass2 XML Payload Format</title>

<author initials="J." surname="Bevendorff" fullname="Janek Bevendorff">
<organization>KeePassXC Team</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email></email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2018" month="February" day="19"/>

<area>Security</area>
<workgroup></workgroup>
<keyword>keepass</keyword>
<keyword>keepassxc</keyword>


<abstract>
<t>This document describes the XML payload format used in KDBX 3.1 and 4.0
containers.  KDBX is an encrypted, XML-based container format for secure
password storage used by KeePass 2.x, KeePassXC and various other password
managers.  This document only describes the actual XML payload and not
the KDBX container format itself.
</t>
</abstract>


<note title="Status of This Memo">
<t>This document is not normative for the KDBX file format; it is
published for informative purposes with the goal to support development
of KDBX-based password management applications.
</t>
<t>The information contained in this document is a work-in-progress reverse
engineering effort of the KDBX file format and likely to be incomplete or
even incorrect at this point in time. This memo is not recommended for
use as reference guide yet.
</t>
</note>


<note title="Copyright Notice">
<t>Copyright (C) 2018 KeePassXC Team
</t>
</note>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>This document describes the payload format used in KDBX (version 3.1 and
4.0) files.  The payload is encoded as XML (&quot;Extensible Markup Language&quot; <xref target="XML"/>).
</t>
<t>KDBX file format versions 3.1 and 4.0 use the same XML structure with minor
differences in the tags supported.  A note is added where KDBX 3.1 and 4.0
differ.
</t>
<t>The XML payload itself is mostly self-contained, but may reference data
from the outer KDBX container. A note is given where this is the case.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions">
<t>In this document, the keywords 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED',
'SHALL', 'SHALL NOT', 'SHOULD', 'SHOULD NOT', 'RECOMMENDED', 'MAY',
and 'OPTIONAL' in capital letters are used to indicate requirements
for the format specification. Their meaning is described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
<t>The term 'Database' refers to the decrypted XML document payload of a
KDBX container.
</t>
<t>Conversely, the term 'KDBX' refers to the full container, including
its encrypted XML payload.
</t>
<t>'Element' refers to an individual XML element inside the database.
</t>

<section anchor="general-database-structure" title="General Database Structure">
<t>A database comprises two main parts: a <spanx style="emph">meta data section</spanx> and the actual
<spanx style="emph">data section</spanx>.
</t>
<t>The meta data section contains general information about the database
itself, maintenance information (e.g., when and how to clean up deleted
entries), access and modification information (e.g., date and time of
the last database title change), and additional global resources (e.g.,
custom icons).
</t>
<t>The data section contains the actual user data as a tree structure of
<spanx style="emph">groups</spanx> and <spanx style="emph">entries</spanx>.
</t>
<t>A <spanx style="emph">group</spanx> is an element with various attributes containing zero or
more <spanx style="emph">entries</spanx>.  A group can also contain zero or more sub groups,
which can again contain groups and entries.  The format of a group
is described in <xref target="groups"/>.
</t>
<t>An <spanx style="emph">entry</spanx> is a set of user credentials and other related data. An entry
MUST have a single parent group.  The attributes of an entry are
described in <xref target="entries"/>.
</t>
<t>A database MUST have exactly one <spanx style="emph">root group</spanx>, which acts as a common
ancestor of all other groups and entries.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="xml-format-description" title="XML Format Description">

<section anchor="xml-schema" title="XML Schema">
<t>A full XML 1.0 schema <xref target="XMLSchema"/> is provided in:
<eref target="kdbx4.0-schema.xsd">kdbx4.0-schema.xsd</eref>
</t>
<t>The schema file is only intended for informative purposes.  In practice,
parsers SHALL NOT use this schema for strict validation.  Most importantly,
parsers SHALL NOT make assumptions about the order of elements.  <spanx style="verb">&lt;xs:sequence&gt;</spanx>
elements are used exclusively for Schema 1.0 compatibility, while in
reality, no particular element order is guaranteed.
</t>
<t>Given the sensitive nature of the data contained in a passwords file,
a parser SHOULD be reasonably forgiving while trying to read the XML
data of a successfully decrypted KDBX file.
</t>

<section anchor="basic-data-types" title="Basic Data Types">
<t>All data stored in a KeePass XML file is UTF-8 string data.  Most XML
elements or attributes can contain arbitrary string values, but some elements
or attributes require special data types, which impose extra restrictions
on the allowed string values.
</t>
<t>The following special data types exist:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>An <spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> is a numeric decimal string consisting of one or more
characters in the range 0 to 9.  <spanx style="emph">INTEGERs</spanx> can have a negative sign <spanx style="verb">-</spanx>
in front.</t>
<t>A <spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> is represented by the strings <spanx style="verb">True</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">False</spanx>.  The
alternative forms <spanx style="verb">true</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">false</spanx>, as well as <spanx style="verb">1</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">0</spanx>, are also
possible.</t>
<t>An <spanx style="emph">OPT BOOLEAN</spanx> is the same as a <spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> with the additional
allowed value <spanx style="verb">Null</spanx> (or <spanx style="verb">null</spanx>) which stands for no definite value.</t>
<t>A <spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> is an XML datetime in ISO 8601 format <xref target="RFC3339"/>.</t>
<t>A <spanx style="emph">COLOR</spanx> is a six-digit hexadecimal RGB color code (characters 0-9
and A-F or a-f), preceded by a # character (e.g., #FF00FF for magenta)</t>
<t>A <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx> is a Base64-encoded <xref target="RFC4648"/> string representation of
arbitrary binary data.</t>
<t>A <spanx style="emph">STRING MAP</spanx> is a complex XML type with exactly two child elements
<spanx style="verb">&lt;Key&gt;</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">&lt;Value&gt;</spanx> describing a mapping between a key string and a
value string.  The <spanx style="verb">&lt;Value&gt;</spanx> element MAY have the <spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> attribute
<spanx style="verb">ProtectInMemory</spanx> to indicate that the value should be protected at
runtime by in-memory encryption.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="protected-elements" title="Protected Elements">
<t>All non-complex XML elements (including elements of the non-complex types
described in <xref target="basic-data-types"/>) MAY have a <spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> <spanx style="verb">Protected</spanx>
attribute.  If this attribute is set to <spanx style="verb">True</spanx>, the element's string data
MUST be a <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx> of encrypted data which must be decrypted before use.
The data MUST be encrypted with the KDBX container's inner random
stream cipher.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="identifiers" title="Identifiers">
<t>Most resources (e.g., groups and entries) inside a database are
identified by a <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx>, which is a globally unique 128-bit (16-byte)
identifier encoded as a <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx>.
</t>
<t>An element of type <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> either directly defines the UUID of a resource
(indicated by <spanx style="emph">KEY</spanx>) or it is used to represent a reference to another
resource identified by this UUID (indicated by <spanx style="emph">REF</spanx>).  If the element is a
reference, but the target is undefined or does not exist, the zero UUID
MUST be used to indicate an invalid reference.  The zero UUID is a 16-tuple
of <spanx style="verb">0x0</spanx> bytes in Base64 encoding (i.e., <spanx style="verb">AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA==</spanx>).
Where allowed, the referencing element MAY also be skipped instead of using
the zero UUID.
</t>
<t>If a <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> element is a reference and the UUID is not the zero UUID,
the referenced resource MUST exist.
</t>
<t>The zero UUID itself MUST NOT be used as a <spanx style="emph">KEY</spanx>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="trivial-changes" title="Trivial Changes">
<t>Most data in a database is generated and updated explicitly by the user.
There exists, however, data that is implicitly generated or updated by
certain (trivial) user actions (e.g. by selecting an entry or copying a
password).  Data that is implicitly updated in this way is classified as
<spanx style="emph">ephemeral data</spanx> and XML elements containing ephemeral data are called
<spanx style="emph">ephemeral elements</spanx> (indicated by <spanx style="emph">EPH</spanx>).
</t>
<t>Changes to <spanx style="emph">EPH</spanx> elements SHOULD NOT mark a database as modified.
Accordingly, the user SHOULD NOT be asked to save changes before closing a
database which has only ephemeral changes.  If an implementation saves
changes automatically without explicit user interaction, ephemeral
changes SHOULD be silently discarded if no other non-ephemeral
changes exist.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="main-elements" title="Main Elements">
<t>A KeePass XML database SHOULD start with an XML declaration.  The encoding of
the XML data MUST be UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"/>.
</t>
<t>The XML document MUST have a root element named <spanx style="verb">&lt;KeePassFile&gt;</spanx>.  The
<spanx style="verb">&lt;KeePassFile&gt;</spanx> root element MUST have exactly two child nodes <spanx style="verb">&lt;Meta&gt;</spanx>
and <spanx style="verb">&lt;Root&gt;</spanx>:
</t>

<figure align="center"><artwork align="center">
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?&gt;
&lt;KeePassFile&gt;
    &lt;Meta&gt;
        &lt;!-- Database meta data --&gt;
    &lt;/Meta&gt;
    &lt;Root&gt;
        &lt;!-- Database root group --&gt;
        &lt;!-- Optional deleted object records --&gt;
    &lt;/Root&gt;
&lt;/KeePassFile&gt;
</artwork></figure>
<t><spanx style="verb">&lt;Meta&gt;</spanx> contains the database's meta data section, while <spanx style="verb">&lt;Root&gt;</spanx>
contains the actual data section, i.e., the root group (see
<xref target="general-database-structure"/>).
</t>
<t>Besides the database's root group, <spanx style="verb">&lt;Root&gt;</spanx> MAY also contain historical
records of deleted objects, whose format is described in <xref target="deleted-objects"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="meta-data-section" title="Meta Data Section">
<t>The <spanx style="verb">&lt;Meta&gt;</spanx> element can contain any of the following elements at most once
to describe various database meta data.
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="&lt;HeaderHash&gt; (KDBX 3.1)">
The SHA-256 <xref target="RFC4634"/> hash of the KDBX header data as <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx>.  This
element is only useful for KDBX 3.1 or lower, but MAY also be present
in KDBX 4.0 or higher.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;SettingsChanged&gt; (KDBX 4.0)">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> of the last change of database meta data or KDBX container
settings.  This element is only specified for KDBX containers <spanx style="strong">version 4.0
or higher</spanx> and MUST NOT be present in KDBX 3.1 or lower.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Generator&gt;">
The name of the program that generated the KDBX file.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DatabaseName&gt;">
An optional name for the database.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DatabaseNameChanged&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> of the last change of <spanx style="verb">&lt;DatabaseName&gt;</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DatabaseDescription&gt;">
An optional description of the database.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DatabaseDescriptionChanged&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> of the last change of <spanx style="verb">&lt;DatabaseDescription&gt;</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DefaultUserName&gt;">
The username to use as a default when creating a new entry in the database.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DefaultUserNameChanged&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> of the last change of <spanx style="verb">&lt;DefaultUserName&gt;</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;MaintenanceHistoryDays&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> indicating the maximum age of the oldest history item
to keep in days when performing database maintenance.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Color&gt;">
A <spanx style="emph">COLOR</spanx> that can be used for coloring the program icon or database tab
inside the password manager application.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;MasterKeyChanged&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> of the last change of the database's master key.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;MasterKeyChangeRec&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> indicating the number of days after which the password manager
SHOULD recommend changing the database's master key (-1 means 'never')</t>
<t hangText="&lt;MasterKeyChangeForce&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> indicating the number of days after which the password manager
SHOULD force changing the database's master key (-1 means 'never')</t>
<t hangText="&lt;MasterKeyChangeForceOnce&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> indicating that the password manager SHOULD force changing the
database's master key next time the database is opened.  This element SHOULD
be removed or set to 'False' once the master key has been changed.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;MemoryProtection&gt;">
A complex XML type for configuring which fields SHOULD be protected by
in-memory encryption at runtime.  The element MAY have the <spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> child
elements <spanx style="verb">&lt;ProtectTitle&gt;</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">&lt;ProtectUserName&gt;</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">&lt;ProtectPassword&gt;</spanx>,
<spanx style="verb">&lt;ProtectURL&gt;</spanx>, and <spanx style="verb">&lt;ProtectNotes&gt;</spanx> for protection of the title, username,
password, URL and notes fields.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;CustomIcons&gt;">
A complex XML type containing a sequence of zero or more custom icons, which
can be used for visually customizing groups and entries (described in <xref target="groups"/>
and <xref target="entries"/>).  An icon is an <spanx style="verb">&lt;Icon&gt;</spanx> element, which has exactly two
children <spanx style="verb">&lt;UUID&gt;</spanx> (a <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx>) and <spanx style="verb">&lt;Data&gt;</spanx>.  <spanx style="verb">&lt;Data&gt;</spanx> contains the icon image
data as <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;RecycleBinEnabled&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> indicating whether the database has an enable recycle bin.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;RecycleBinUUID&gt; (REF)">
The <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> of the recycle bin group inside the database.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;RecycleBinChanged&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> of the last change to the recycle bin.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;EntryTemplatesGroup&gt; (REF)">
The <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> of the group that contains templates for the creation of
new entries.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;EntryTemplatesGroupChanged&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> of the last change to the templates group.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;HistoryMaxItems&gt;">
An <spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> indicating the maximum number of items the history of
an element may have (history items are described in <xref target="entry-history"/>).
When the number of items in an entry's history exceeds this number, the
password manager SHOULD delete the oldest history items until the number
of history items no longer exceeds this value.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;HistoryMaxSize&gt;">
An <spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> indicating the maximum history size in bytes. If an entry's
history exceeds this size, the password manager SHOULD delete the oldest
history items, until the total history size no longer exceeds this value.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;LastSelectedGroup&gt; (REF, EPH)">
<spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> of the group that was last selected by the user.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;LastTopVisibleGroup&gt; (REF, EPH)">
<spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> of the top-most group that is still visible in the user's current
scroll view.  GUI implementations MAY use this element to save the
scroll state of the groups tree.  If an implementation decides not to store
scroll information, this SHOULD point to the root group.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Binaries&gt; (KDBX 3.1)">
A sequence of zero or more <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> elements containing files attached
to entries in the database.  Each <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> element is a <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx> containing
the file's contents. <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> elements MUST have an <spanx style="verb">ID</spanx> attribute,
which is a unique <spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> identifying the <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx> data and a <spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx>
attribute <spanx style="verb">Compressed</spanx>, indicating whether the <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx> data is
Gzip-compressed <xref target="RFC1952"/>.

<vspace/>
A database SHOULD NOT contain two <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> elements with the same
<spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx> data.

<vspace/>
This element is only specified for KDBX 3.1 and lower.  KDBX 4.0 stores
files in its encrypted binary inner header, so this element MUST NOT be
present if the container format is version 4.0 or higher.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;CustomData&gt;">
A sequence of zero or more <spanx style="emph">STRING MAP</spanx> <spanx style="verb">&lt;Item&gt;</spanx> elements. <spanx style="verb">&lt;Item&gt;</spanx>
elements can be used by plugins to store arbitrary string data at database
level.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="data-section" title="Data Section">

<section anchor="groups" title="Groups">
<t>Groups in a database are structured as a tree. There MUST be exactly one
root group inside the <spanx style="verb">&lt;Root&gt;</spanx> element.  This root group MAY contain an
arbitrary number of sub groups and entries.  A detailed description of
the database structure was given in <xref target="general-database-structure"/>.
</t>
<t>A group is represented by a <spanx style="verb">&lt;Group&gt;</spanx> element, which MUST have a <spanx style="verb">&lt;UUID&gt;</spanx>
child element of type <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> defining the <spanx style="emph">KEY</spanx> of this group.
</t>
<t>Any <spanx style="verb">&lt;Group&gt;</spanx> element inside another <spanx style="verb">&lt;Group&gt;</spanx> element is a sub group.
<spanx style="verb">&lt;Entry&gt;</spanx> elements inside a <spanx style="verb">&lt;Group&gt;</spanx> element are child entries of that group
(see <xref target="entries"/>).
</t>
<t>In addition, a group can have any of the following child elements at most once:
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="&lt;Name&gt;">
A user-specified name for this group.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Notes&gt;">
Additional notes which the user may save with this group.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;IconID&gt;">
The <spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> identifier of a standard icon to display for this group.
Standard icons are described in <xref target="standard-icons"/></t>
<t hangText="&lt;CustomIconUUID&gt; (REF)">
This element MAY be used to reference to a custom group icon from the
<spanx style="verb">&lt;CustomIcons&gt;</spanx> element of the database's meta data section.
If a non-zero UUID is specified, the referenced custom icon
MUST be used instead of the default icon set in <spanx style="verb">&lt;IconID&gt;</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Times&gt;">
A complex XML type containing information about the group's last access,
modification, or expiry date and time. A detailed description is given in
<xref target="times-and-expiry"/>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;IsExpanded&gt; (EPH)">
If a GUI implementation allows the user to expand and collapse sub trees,
this element MAY contain a <spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> indicating whether this group is
expanded (<spanx style="verb">True</spanx>) or collapsed (<spanx style="verb">False</spanx>).  A collapsed group hides all
it's child groups when displayed as a tree.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DefaultAutoTypeSequence&gt;">
The default Auto-Type sequence to use for entries and sub groups in this
group.  This overrides an implementation's default Auto-Type sequence.
Sub groups or entries may again override this value.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;EnableAutoType&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">OPT BOOLEAN</spanx> for enabling or disabling Auto-Type for this group, its
entries and sub groups.  <spanx style="verb">Null</spanx> inherits a definitive value from the
parent group.  If this is the root group, <spanx style="verb">Null</spanx> is equivalent to <spanx style="verb">True</spanx>.
Individual sub groups may override this value.  If a group enables
Auto-Type, individual entries in this group may still choose to disable it.
However, disabling Auto-Type at group level SHOULD disable it for all direct
child entries, regardless of their setting.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;EnableSearching&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">OPT BOOLEAN</spanx> indicating whether entries in this group should be included
in search results if the user searches the database.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;LastTopVisibleEntry&gt; (REF, EPH)">
Similarly to <spanx style="verb">&lt;LastTopVisibleGroup&gt;</spanx> in the database meta section, this
saves a <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> reference to the top-most entry inside this group that
is still visible inside the user's current scroll view.  GUI
implementations MAY use this element to save the scroll state of
individual groups.  If the group has no entries, this reference MUST point
to the zero UUID.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;CustomData&gt; (KDBX 4.0)">
A sequence of zero or more <spanx style="emph">STRING MAP</spanx> <spanx style="verb">&lt;Item&gt;</spanx> elements. <spanx style="verb">&lt;Item&gt;</spanx>
elements can be used by plugins to store arbitrary string data.  This is
the same as the <spanx style="verb">&lt;CustomData&gt;</spanx> element from the database meta data section,
but at group level.  This element MUST NOT be present if the container
format is KDBX 3.1 or lower.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="entries" title="Entries">
<t>An entry is where the user saves their actual secret data and credentials.
</t>
<t>An entry is represented by an <spanx style="verb">&lt;Entry&gt;</spanx> element, which MUST be a child
of a <spanx style="verb">&lt;Group&gt;</spanx> element.  Like <spanx style="verb">&lt;Group&gt;</spanx>, an <spanx style="verb">&lt;Entry&gt;</spanx> MUST have a <spanx style="verb">&lt;UUID&gt;</spanx>
child element of type <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> defining the <spanx style="emph">KEY</spanx> of this entry.
</t>
<t>For storing the actual data, an entry can have an arbitrary number of
<spanx style="verb">&lt;String&gt;</spanx> elements of type <spanx style="emph">STRING MAP</spanx>.  Besides arbitrary user-defined
keys, the following keys SHOULD be present and displayed as dedicated
input fields and display columns:
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Title">
The entry title.</t>
<t hangText="UserName">
The username of this entry.</t>
<t hangText="Password">
The password of this entry.</t>
<t hangText="URL">
A URL to a remote location which this entry is used for.  An implementation
SHOULD render this as a clickable link that launches a program associated
with the URL's scheme.  The cmd:// scheme SHOULD execute arbitrary commands.</t>
<t hangText="Notes">
Additional notes the user may save with this entry.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>In addition to <spanx style="verb">&lt;String&gt;</spanx> elements, an entry can also have an arbitrary number
of<spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> elements.  This element is has a complex XML type defining a
reference to a file attachment.  The structure of this type is similar to
<spanx style="emph">STRING MAP</spanx> in that it MUST have an element <spanx style="verb">&lt;Key&gt;</spanx>, setting a key for this
attachment (usually the file name) and an element <spanx style="verb">&lt;Value&gt;</spanx>.
</t>
<t>Though unlike <spanx style="emph">STRING MAP</spanx>, the <spanx style="verb">&lt;Value&gt;</spanx> element MUST <spanx style="emph">either</spanx> have an <spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx>
<spanx style="verb">Ref</spanx> attribute and no content <spanx style="emph">or</spanx> the raw attachment data as <spanx style="emph">BLOB</spanx> and no
attribute.  There are also no attributes for in-memory encryption.
</t>
<t>For KDBX 3.1 or lower, the <spanx style="verb">Ref</spanx> attribute references a <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> from
the <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binaries&gt;</spanx> element inside the database's meta data section by its <spanx style="verb">ID</spanx>
attribute.
</t>
<t>For KDBX 4.0 or higher, it references an item from the container's encrypted
binary inner header by its position.
</t>
<t>If the container format is KDBX 4.0 or higher, an entry MAY also have a
<spanx style="verb">&lt;CustomData&gt;</spanx> element for saving arbitrary plugin data, identical to the one
that can be set at group level.  See <xref target="groups"/> for a description of this element.
As for groups, the container format MUST be KDBX 4.0 or higher if this
element exists.
</t>

<section anchor="fixed-data" title="Fixed Data">
<t>Besides arbitrarily many <spanx style="verb">&lt;String&gt;</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> elements, the following
<spanx style="emph">fixed-data</spanx> elements can occur at most once:
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="&lt;IconID&gt;">
The <spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> identifier of a standard icon to display for this group.
Standard icons are described in <xref target="standard-icons"/></t>
<t hangText="&lt;ForegroundColor&gt;">
A <spanx style="emph">COLOR</spanx> to be used as custom entry text color.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;BackgroundColor&gt;">
A <spanx style="emph">COLOR</spanx> to be used as custom entry background color.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;OverrideURL&gt;">
An additional URL that overrides the triggered target when the user
clicks the Link generated from the <spanx style="verb">URL</spanx> string field.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Tags&gt;">
A list of used-defined tags for this entry separated by semicolons <spanx style="verb">;</spanx>.
Tags allow to classify entries orthogonally to the group hierarchy.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Times&gt;">
A complex XML type containing information about this entry's last access,
modification, or expiry date and time. A detailed description is given in
<xref target="times-and-expiry"/>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;AutoType&gt;">
A complex XML type containing information about this entry's Auto-Type
settings. A detailed description is given in <xref target="autotype-settings"/>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;History&gt;">
A sequence of previous versions of this entry.  History items are
described in <xref target="entry-history"/>.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="autotype-settings" title="Auto-Type Settings">
<t>An implementation SHOULD try to match window titles for Auto-Type automatically
with data from an entry and use <spanx style="verb">{USERNAME}{TAB}{PASSWORD}{ENTER}</spanx> as a default
Auto-Type sequence.  To lower the risk of accidental submission to wrong input
forms, it MAY also reduce the default sequence to <spanx style="verb">{USERNAME}{TAB}{PASSWORD}</spanx>.
</t>
<t>An entry MAY specify additional Auto-Type settings, which override the default
Auto-Type settings provided by the implementation.  This is done in an
<spanx style="verb">&lt;AutoType&gt;</spanx> element inside the <spanx style="verb">&lt;Entry&gt;</spanx>.  The following child elements are
possible and can occur at most once:
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="&lt;Enabled&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> indicating whether Auto-Type should be enabled for this entry.
The default SHOULD be <spanx style="verb">True</spanx>.  If Auto-Type is enabled for the parent group,
this can be used to override the setting.  On the other hand, if Auto-Type
is disabled for the parent group, this setting SHOULD have no effect.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DataTransferObfuscation&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> indicating whether an implementation MAY try to obfuscate Auto-Type
key strokes to make it harder for key loggers to record the full sequence.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;DefaultSequence&gt;">
The default Auto-Type sequence to use for this entry (overrides the global
or group default).</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Additionally, the user SHOULD be able to add additional window associations to
an entry.  A window association is a specific Auto-Type setting for a specific
window.  An entry can hold an arbitrary number of <spanx style="verb">&lt;Association&gt;</spanx> elements,
one for every individual window association.
</t>
<t>An <spanx style="verb">&lt;Association&gt;</spanx> MUST have the following two elements:
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="&lt;Window&gt;">
The title of the window to match with this entry.  The string MUST support
<spanx style="verb">*</spanx> as a wildcard character.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;KeystrokeSequence&gt;">
A custom Auto-Type sequence.  If the value is left empty, the sequence
from <spanx style="verb">&lt;DefaultSequence&gt;</spanx> is used or, if that is empty as well, the group
or global default.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="entry-history" title="Entry History">
<t>To improve robustness against user credential loss by accidental edits, all
changes to an entry SHOULD be recorded in an entry's history.
</t>
<t>For this, an implementation SHOULD create a copy of an entry (excluding its
history) and add it to the original entry's <spanx style="verb">&lt;History&gt;</spanx> before applying any
modifications to the original entry.  This applies to all user-initiated,
non-ephemeral database changes which would result in an updated KDBX file
when saved.
</t>
<t>A history item SHOULD be created immediately when the user commits a change
to the database, not only when the updated KDBX file is actually saved to
disk.
</t>
<t>The newest history item MUST be last in the list.  Copying and adding an item
to the history MUST NOT change any of its elements. This also applies to all
ephemeral elements.  The history item MUST capture the exact state of the
original element before modification.
</t>
<t>After adding a new history item, an implementation SHOULD ensure that the
history does not grow larger than the configured limits.
</t>
<t>If the new number of history items exceeds the value configured in the
<spanx style="verb">&lt;HistoryMaxItems&gt;</spanx> setting from the databases meta data, the oldest history
items SHOULD be deleted until the number of actual history items does not
exceed this number anymore.
</t>
<t>Similarly, if the total size of the history in bytes exceeds
<spanx style="verb">&lt;HistoryMaxSize&gt;</spanx>, the oldest items SHOULD be deleted, until the total size
does not exceed this number anymore.  The size of the history is calculated by
adding the sizes of all entries in the history.
</t>
<t>The size of an entry SHOULD be calculated as the sum of its UTF-8 string data
in bytes, including all <spanx style="verb">&lt;String&gt;</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx>, and <spanx style="verb">&lt;CustomData&gt;</spanx> keys and
values, Auto-Type <spanx style="verb">&lt;Association&gt;</spanx> window titles and sequences, <spanx style="verb">&lt;Tags&gt;</spanx>,
<spanx style="verb">&lt;OverrideURL&gt;</spanx> and the remaining fixed data.  For simplicity, the latter
MAY be estimated as <spanx style="verb">128</spanx>.
</t>
<t>The size of <spanx style="verb">&lt;Binary&gt;</spanx> values SHOULD calculated <spanx style="emph">after</spanx> Base64 decoding.
</t>
<t>An implementation MAY also provide a manual or automatic database maintenance
feature, which deletes all history items older than <spanx style="verb">&lt;MaintenanceHistoryDays&gt;</spanx>.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="times-and-expiry" title="Times And Expiry">
<t>Groups and entries (hereafter called <spanx style="emph">items</spanx>) MAY have a <spanx style="verb">&lt;Times&gt;</spanx> element
recording and configuring various time- and usage-based data.  If present,
the <spanx style="verb">&lt;Times&gt;</spanx> element can have any the following child elements at most once:
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="&lt;CreationTime&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> when the item was created.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;LastModificationTime&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> when the item was last modified.  If it was newly created,
this SHOULD be the same as <spanx style="verb">&lt;CreationTime&gt;</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;LastAccessTime&gt; (EPH)">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> when this item was last accessed.  Any kind of access MAY update
this element, including data modification and item relocation, but also
trivial tasks such as viewing an item's data, copying its data to the
clipboard etc.  If an items was newly created, this SHOULD be the same as
<spanx style="verb">&lt;CreationTime&gt;</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;ExpiryTime&gt;">
User-configurable <spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> when this item will expire.  An expired item
SHOULD be marked in a special and distinguishable way (e.g., with a special
icon or crossed out), so the user can easily spot expired items.  An
implementation MAY also choose to hide expired items or display them in a
special location.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;Expires&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">BOOLEAN</spanx> indicating whether this item will expire.  If this is set to <spanx style="verb">False</spanx>,
<spanx style="verb">&lt;ExpiryTime&gt;</spanx> has no effect.  If this element is missing, a default value
of <spanx style="verb">False</spanx> is assumed.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;UsageCount&gt; (EPH)">
<spanx style="emph">INTEGER</spanx> recording the number of times this item was used or accessed.
Any kind of usage / access MAY update this element.  These kinds of usage
SHOULD be the same that also update <spanx style="verb">&lt;LastAccessTime&gt;</spanx>.</t>
<t hangText="&lt;LocationChanged&gt;">
<spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> when this item was last re-located inside the group hierarchy.
This MAY be updated whenever the parent of an item changes.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="deleted-objects" title="Deleted Objects">
<t>When a group or an entry is deleted, an implementation MAY add a note about
this deletion in <spanx style="verb">&lt;DeletedObjects&gt;</spanx> of the data section.  This is to allow proper
two-way remote synchronization of databases.
</t>
<t>Such a note is a <spanx style="verb">&lt;DeletedObject&gt;</spanx> element, which MUST have a <spanx style="verb">&lt;UUID&gt;</spanx> element
of type <spanx style="emph">UUID</spanx> (<spanx style="emph">KEY</spanx>) with the UUID of the deleted object and a <spanx style="verb">&lt;DeletionTime&gt;</spanx>
element of type <spanx style="emph">DATETIME</spanx> recording the date and time this item was deleted.
</t>
<t>If an implementation keeps track of deleted groups and entries, it SHOULD also
provide an automatic or manual maintenance feature to clean up old deleted object
notes.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="standard-icons" title="Standard Icons">
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>KDBX is an encrypted container format.  The security of the XML payload
described in this document depends on the strength of the cipher and
passphrase / key file used for encrypting the encapsulating KDBX container.
</t>
<t>In addition, all security considerations for <xref target="XML"/> apply as well,
including the use of recursive XML entities, which can consume an
arbitrarily large amount of memory on the user's system during parsing.
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml"?>
<reference anchor="XML" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126/">
    <front>
        <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth Edition)</title>
        <author initials="T." surname="Bray" fullname="Tim Bray">
            <organization>Textuality and Netscape</organization>
            <address>
                <email>tbray@textuality.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="J." surname="Paoli" fullname="Jean Paoli">
            <organization>Microsoft</organization>
            <address>
                <email>jeanpa@microsoft.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="C. M." surname="Sperberg-McQueen" fullname="C. M. Sperberg-McQueen">
            <organization>W3C</organization>
            <address>
                <email>cmsmcq@w3.org</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="E." surname="Eve" fullname="Eve Maler">
            <organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <email>eve.maler@east.sun.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="F." surname="Yergeau" fullname="François Yergeau"/>
        <date day="26" month="November" year="2008"/>
    </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="XMLSchema" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-1/">
    <front>
        <title>XML Schema Part 1: Structures Second Edition</title>
        <author initials="H. S." surname="Thompson" fullname="Henry S. Thompson">
            <organization>University of Edinburgh</organization>
            <address>
                <email>ht@cogsci.ed.ac.uk</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="D." surname="Beech" fullname="David Beech">
            <organization>Oracle Corporation</organization>
            <address>
                <email>David.Beech@oracle.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Maloney" fullname="Murray Maloney">
            <organization>Commerce One</organization>
            <address>
                <email>murray@muzmo.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="N." surname="Mendelsohn" fullname="Noah Mendelsohn">
            <organization>Lotus Development Corporation</organization>
            <address>
                <email>Noah_Mendelsohn@lotus.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date day="28" month="October" year="2004"/>
    </front>
</reference>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1952.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4634.xml"?>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
